[Music]
so this is a review of the Oracle touch
espresso machine now it's made by a
company called sage in the UK or better
known as Breville in the rest of the
world now I'll start with the truth
which is for a decade I haven't had an
espresso machine at home and to be
honest I haven't really wanted one when
people ask me what espresso machine
should I get for my house well I asked
them a question back do you really want
a new hobby
because that's what espresso at home is
for most people it's an investment in
equipment but it's also an investment in
time when I got started working in
coffee I started selling little domestic
espresso machines and I know all too
well that the romantic idea of getting
up at the weekend reading the paper
making a little cappuccino that's very
appealing to people but it's not true
you skip the bit where you turn on the
machine you wait for it to get hot then
you dial in two three shots to see how
things are tasting then you pull a
couple of shots and then you spend some
time cleaning up and for me well the
idea of paying two pounds for someone
else to do that to make me an espresso
that seemed like a good deal and at home
I typically just brewed filter coffee so
taking this home for a little while well
that was the first time in literally ten
years I've made us Brussels at home and
it was interesting this is a 2,000 pound
espresso machine and that's quite a lot
of money these days and a lot of money
to invest in an espresso machine
especially in one that's labeled as a
bean to cup
the people who didn't want a hobby that
was kind of your choice right you you if
you didn't want to do all the hard work
then you just push a button and the
machine did its best and you got coffee
and they all had a problem that made
them quite finicky quite difficult to
extract well with and prone to breaking
down they were trying to work out how to
get coffee from a grinder into a brewing
chamber and then to get rid of it and
that moving of ground coffee both wet
and dry is pretty difficult to do and
sages solutions pretty simple you just
get the human to do it so this machine
comes with a porta filter and a grinder
and it's all built in as one and you're
going to be the one that moves ground
coffee around that's going to be your
contribution to the brewing process so
the way this thing works is kind of
interesting because it's kind of against
the typical obsessive geeky want to
control every factor and they know
espresso making is hard and so what
they've done is take away some of the
variables what this means is that the
way the grinder works is that when you
lock it in click it into place and you
click across to the right hand side
it'll start grinding it'll grind dose
tamp the whole deal all in one go
leaving you a prepped portafilter ready
to brew so you lock that in and you hit
go now it's a touchscreen and this means
you've got lots of choices and what it
lets you do is choose the different kind
of drinks you want to make choose the
grime setting and choose the brew time
for each one then that's another key
part this doesn't let you control the
amount of liquid going through in like a
volumetric might or with weighing scales
or something like that it's going to
brew at a fixed pressure for a fixed
amount of time now this is no bad thing
by and large what you might want to do
is use your consistent dose setting and
therefore use a consistent brew time and
then simply adjust the grind setting
final or coarser to get the desired
amount of liquid that you want in the
kind of ideal brew time so I'll just set
the brew time to 28 seconds I'll just
use my grind settings to control my
espresso brew ratio speaking about brew
ratios
this thing the setup it has it doses
quite a lot of coffee into the
portafilter it's kind of dependent on
the basket that you're using typically I
brew coffees that taste good at a 1/2 to
about one to two point two as a ratio so
if I put 20 grams in I'm getting between
40 and 44 grams of liquid out in my
desired brew time here I'd probably say
with those kind of coffees you probably
want to push them at least to one to 2.5
so if you have 20 grams of ground coffee
you probably want about 50 grams of
liquid out so to be honest with
certainly lighter roasts shorter tighter
shots of espresso closer to a ristretto
even like a traditional normal espresso
they're a little bit harder to do if you
enjoy that kind of thing and you're a
texture driven then lighter roasts may
not be the answer for you and you may
want to brew with a slightly deeper more
developed roast that's gonna give itself
up a little bit more easily sage made
waves with their first espresso machine
have really good temperature control all
of that stuff is still here so they've
done the kind of hard work on on
consistency and control while trying not
to overload you with too many variables
so it brews pretty good tasting espresso
I got some very tasty shots out of it it
was pretty easy to use
it required reconfiguring how my brain
works a little bit with the fixed dose
and and fixed time and just manipulating
with grind but I didn't mind that too
much at all one thing that this machine
does incredibly well and Sage have done
for a little while now is steam milk
beautifully now this the automatic
steaming of milk is is not new on
commercial equipment for sure you know
there's been big commercial espresso
machines that have been able to
automatically texture milk to a really
beautiful foam certainly you can pour
great latte out with it that's been
around for a while but these guys have
been doing it more and more on domestic
machines and the quality is
frustratingly good when you can do
something that good at home you really
have to question why this kind of
technology just isn't everywhere all the
time and I get that you know the lack of
craft may upset some people but there's
really no excuse left in the world of
serving anything other
than a really beautifully textured milk
drink even if you can't pull a TI on the
top and should still have great texture
that technology is now very much
available so a couple quick things you
can program your milk temperature it has
a little thermocouple at the end of the
steam wand there that senses the milk
temperature and stops at the right point
you can adjust texture of the milk as
well and one neat little feature is when
you're finished steaming when you push
the steam wand back in it purges itself
automatically again just thoughtful use
of technology to make our lives a little
bit easier
a few quick likes and don't likes things
I like the touchscreen actually it's
great if this is not a Wi-Fi enabled
machine but having a touchscreen means
you can do walk through for setting it
up you can do troubleshooting you can
offer a lot of guidance the touch screen
is perfectly fine in terms of usability
I think that's a really nice upgrade to
these kind of machines
I think the steaming is excellent one
thing and I particularly love is that
when you remove the drip tray and if you
twist the dial you can just move your
machine around the counter really really
easily that's just great
I love that you can load water in the
top so you can fill from the front if
you put your machine in your kitchens at
the back but you still have a fully
removable water tank that can be
accessed from the back that's kind of
nice thinking things I don't love as
much the grinder does suffer the same
problem that many other grinders do
which is as it gets hotter as you use it
more its grind setting does shift a
little bit so what I would tend to do is
because I would just make a couple of
drinks in the morning and that was it I
would have the Machine switch itself on
about half an hour before I wanted to
get up it was nice and hot I would come
down pull a shot clean up be done if I
had to pull two three four or five shots
then I know my grind would change but at
the end of doing that I would just reset
my grinder back to the original number
that way when I woke up the next morning
and it was ready to pull its first shot
of the day it was at the right grind
setting and ground settings held pretty
well for me in testing for me the
grinder is okay I kind of wish I had
more control again and again I wish I
had a little bit more control over the
dose going in typically these doses are
pretty high
and that's not how I usually brew coffee
so again I'm probably not the target
audience here but I have to be honest in
the things that I would want to change
or want more control over and lastly
there is the price point it's 2,000
pounds that's not cheap and I know that
that's not a bad thing you get really
well-built good quality machine you get
good support in the UK and other places
but you can't help but mention that
price it's a little bit higher than a
lot of other domestic being two cups
that said I would anticipate you're
gonna have a lot less issues this can
run you through your own descaling
programs there's just less parts to go
wrong compared to a traditional bean to
cup in summary if you are an espresso
obsessive and you want to play with your
coffee this is probably not the machine
for you it won't offer you enough
control enough granularity about your
coffee brewing if you're someone who
does actually want that coffee at home
cappuccinos in the morning a little flat
white but you don't want a new hobby
well I guess sage have built this
machine for you and I have to say
they've done a pretty good job thank you
very much for watching if you want to
comment if you want to ask a question
ask it down below I will do my best to
answer every one if you enjoyed this let
me know if you have someone in your life
who got one of these for Christmas send
this their way go and see them go and
have a copy see what you think I'll be
back with some more reviews in the new
year thanks for watching and have a good
one